<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact narrative of the affection, services, sufferings, and expences of Capt. Reeve Williams; both at sea and land for the advantage of the publique interest of the Common-wealth of England; from the beginning of the late vvarre to this present: humbly tendered unto the consideration of His Excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and all other persons of honour and ingenuity, whom it may or shall concerne.</title>
            <author>Williams, Reeve, Capt.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2753A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2450:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact narrative of the affection, services, sufferings, and expences of Capt. Reeve Williams; both at sea and land for the advantage of the publique interest of the Common-wealth of England; from the beginning of the late vvarre to this present: humbly tendered unto the consideration of His Excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and all other persons of honour and ingenuity, whom it may or shall concerne.</title>
                  <author>Williams, Reeve, Capt.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137214:1"/>
            <p>AN EXACT NARRATIVE OF THE Affection, Services, Sufferings, and Expences OF Capt. <hi>REEVE WILIIAMS,</hi> Both at SEA and LAND, For the advantage of the publique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Common-wealth of <hi>ENGLAND;</hi> From the beginning of the late VVarre to this preſent: Humbly tendered unto the conſideration of His EXCELLENCY the LORD GENERAL <hi>CROMWELL,</hi> And all other perſons of Honour and Ingenuity, whom it may or ſhall concerne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Yeare 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:137214:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137214:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which enduced me to preſent your <hi>EXCELLENCY</hi> with this ſhort Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of my Services, Sufferings, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſements for this Nation, proceedeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the vanity to magnifie my owne actions (being hardly worth the mentioning before your <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi>) Nor from any preſsing neceſsity of your pitty; or a preſent deſire to be re-imburſed, though I do very much need both your compaſsion &amp; aſsiſtance: but the ſame principles of Reaſon, Honour, and Juſtice, (that obliged my primitive en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with the firſt for this Nation in generall, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of its Lawes and Liberties) calling upon me to make ſome ſure proviſion, that after my long and faithfull ſervice, travells and endeavours for the publique Weale, I my ſelfe might not lye under a cauſeleſſe calumny, doth neceſsitate this my humble application to your <hi>Excellency,</hi> to the end that (my cauſe being fully knowne) I might not be rendered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of an owning from your <hi>Excellency,</hi> and all good men that have acted though in a higher ſtation) on the ſame account.</p>
            <p>I have onely hinted herein at what I have ſuffered in that kind, without recrimination, and am really as free from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content thereby, as thoſe who in reward of their endeavours have received greater encouragement; and if your <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> ſhall daigne to conſider the enſuing Narrative; and upon due conſideration thereof upon principles of reaſon, in
<pb facs="tcp:137214:3"/>your owne judgement conclude me a lover of my Country, I ſhall eſteeme my ſelfe no loſer, by all thoſe hazards, ſervices, and expences I have undergone, upon the account of the Publique, it having heitherto (through mercy) been alwaies by me a concluſive ſatisfaction, that the diſpenſation of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, had or did hand them out to me as a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient patrimony.</p>
            <p>My Lord, The aſſurance that I have of your <hi>Excellencies</hi> love to Juſtice, and enlarged affections frequently evidenced to ſuch as have been faithful, together with the inward peace I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take as having done all things ſingly, with Zeale, fervour, and faithfulneſſe, hath created in me an exceeding confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that neither my perſon can any way want encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor my cauſe conſideration, while my ſelfe and it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine under the protection of your <hi>Excellency;</hi> to whom I in all humility make my appeale, as depending on your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (thereto encouraged by former favours) I ſhall with the greateſt aſſurance depend; being with all thankfulneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Excellencies affectionate and moſt obedient Servant, Reeve VVilliams.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137214:3"/>
            <head>The Affection, Services, Sufferings, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of C. <hi>Reeve Williams</hi> for the preſervation of the Engliſh intereſt, on behalf of the Parl. and Army from the beginning of the Warre to this preſent. Tendered unto the ſerious conſideration of his Excellencie The LORD GENERALL, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing convinced in his underſtanding of the juſtneſſe of the Parliaments cauſe in oppoſition to the King and his adherents, and deſiring to manifeſt his affection thereunto. In <hi>Anno</hi> 1641. he at his owne charge fitted a Ship at <hi>Dover</hi> to be imployed in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the State againſt the Iriſh; but when he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended a very great part of his eſtate therein, Impreſt was denyed him, and he being a ſtranger in thoſe parts, and not able to beare the whole charge) was forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with the ſaid Ship to <hi>Wales,</hi> there to Winter, and remaine untill Providence ſhould offer an opportunity of his being ſerviceable to the State, which fell according to his expectation; for immediatly after the Battle at <hi>Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> the late King ſent one Col: <hi>Donell</hi> to <hi>Swanſey</hi> to ſeize upon the ſaid Ship, and in her to import Armes and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition from <hi>France;</hi> but Capt: <hi>Williams</hi> having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, took his opportunity and ſet ſayle with the ſaid Ship to <hi>Plimouth</hi> immediately; for which he was proclaimed a Traytor to the King. But being ſafely ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, and having ſupplyed the Town with ſome proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he took a Commiſſion from the Earle of <hi>Stamford</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:137214:4"/>then Generall of the Weſt of <hi>England;</hi> and hearing the County of <hi>Pembroke</hi> was much ſtraitned, and in apparent danger of being loſt to the enemy, the well-affected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt quite diſmay'd, having very few friends, many irreconcileable enemies, and no one Ship of force belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Parliament in their Harbour to ſupport them, he ſet ſayle to <hi>Milford haven:</hi> At whoſe arrivall, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments friends were much encouraged to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the enemy, who were preparing to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and the enemy no leſſe diſcouraged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. From thence he ſteered to <hi>Ireland,</hi> to Admirall <hi>Swanley,</hi> to whom he diſcovered the neceſſity of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments friends in <hi>Pembrokeſhire,</hi> with the advantage that might accrue to the Parl. intereſt, if he would with any of his Ships of War but appeare to countenance and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them. Whereupon Admirall <hi>Swanley</hi> being ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly affected therewith, ſent Vice-Admirall <hi>Smith</hi> with Capt. <hi>Williams</hi> to <hi>Milford,</hi> where arriving they found two men of Warre of the Kings riding in the Harbour, &amp; threatning fire and ſword to the Country, if they did not relinquiſh the Parl. intereſt, and adhere to the Kings; both which were taken, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> by Captaine <hi>Smith,</hi> and the <hi>Hart</hi> Frigot by Capt: <hi>Williams,</hi> after 24. houres fight, to the great hazard of his own Ship.</p>
            <p>Soone after he reduced the Town of <hi>Tinby</hi> to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Parl. and obliged them to receive a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from Maj: Gen: <hi>Laughorne,</hi> although the town at that time had onely Capt: <hi>Wyat</hi> and Capt: <hi>Gibs</hi> and their rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that were in the ſaid Town, friends to the Parl.</p>
            <p>All which ſervices, expences and hazards were by him performed upon the ſingle ſcore of Affection, he having received no aſſurance of pay or ſatisfaction from the Par. that might or did in any meaſure induce him thereto.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:137214:4"/>
            <p>Neither reſted he there; but with his Prize taken as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſayled to the Downes, where appearing to the Admirall and his ſervice by Vice-Admirall <hi>Smith</hi> to him manifeſted, the ſame was repreſented to the Parliament, to whoſe Officers he had delivered his Prize at <hi>Chattam,</hi> with all her ſtores and tackle unimbezel'd, for which he received a publique owning from the Parliament, and was with his Ship entertained in the publique ſervice; and in a ſhort time was inſtrumentall in the bringing in many rich Prizes, which were diſpoſed for the ſervice of the Parl.</p>
            <p>The next yeare having with the Parl. Commiſſion put to Sea for his owne account, he was taken by three of the French Kings Men of War and carryed into <hi>Breſt,</hi> where his Ship was ſold, and he himſelfe after many hardſhips and hazards eſcaped with life to <hi>England,</hi> by which he was damnified in his eſtate, as is proved in the Admiralty, above 6000. l. all which loſſes and hazards he ſuſtained for no other cauſe but his conſtant adherence to, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the intereſt of Parl. from whom as a reward and encouragement he received a promiſe of reparation.</p>
            <p>Being diſabled in his eſtate as aforeſaid, he reſolved ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe to engage againe according to his ability: In order to which, with the aſſiſtance of ſome friends, he built a Frigot with 32. Oares, with which he re-took the Scout Frigot formerly loſt, ſunk the Frigot called <hi>The Cavalier of Briſtoll,</hi> that infeſted the Weſtern coaſt, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Weymouth;</hi> alſo a Frigot of S. <hi>Mallowes,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſupplyed the Kings party with Arms and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition.</p>
            <p>After which, and ſeverall other ſervices done for the Publique, he returned to <hi>London;</hi> where reſiding ſome ſmall time, and finding the power of the enemy at Sea increaſing, he againe caſt himſelfe upon Providence, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137214:5"/>with three Ships, <hi>viz.</hi> the Mermaid, the Warſpite, and the Increaſe, fitted, victualled, and mann'd upon his own accompt he ſet out to Sea; and being outward bound in <hi>Bolloign</hi> Roade, he tooke the <hi>Charles</hi> Frigot belonging to Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſpe,</hi> which had long infeſted the Coaſt of <hi>Kent,</hi> and done much miſchiefe to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments friends; which Frigot was alſo added to his Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, and a Commiſſion obtained for her; ſoon after, ranging in the Chanell he took the Princes Dogger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Boat, a veſſell of eight Gunns, laden with proviſions for <hi>Pendennis</hi> fort, and a packquet directed to Sir <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Criſpe;</hi> which being tranſmitted to the State, he ſteered toward the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as well to prevent ſupplyes conſigned to the Iriſh from other Nations, as to make his purchaſe upon them. Where arriving, on the South Weſt part of <hi>Munſter</hi> at <hi>Barnet Shillock,</hi> he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly landed ſome men, and forcing the Iriſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to the mountains, he ſeiz'd upon a Magazine of the enemies, conſiſting of a good quantity of Powder, Match, Beere, <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> Salt Salmon, &amp;c. all which he carried on board without any loſſe, notwithſtanding the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of 120. Muskettiers lodg'd in an adjacent thicket, that endeavoured to prevent the ſame, the ſaid <hi>Ambuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cado</hi> being forced to retreat to a Village, from whence they were beaten alſo, and the Village Plundred, Burnt and deſtroyed, together with the Magazine thereunto belonging; after which, he retired to his Ship without the loſſe of any one man, ſo great was the mercy of God in his preſervation.</p>
            <p>From hence he ſayled into the <hi>Bay</hi> of the <hi>Bantery,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a deſigne on the Town of <hi>Dingle de Couch,</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it had been newly ſacked by Admirall <hi>Moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> he went to Anchor in the ſound of the <hi>Blasketts,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:137214:5"/>where hareing that a Flemiſh Ship was that day gone into the ſaid Town of <hi>Dingle,</hi> he preſently ſent the Warſpite and the Increaſe, to attempt the bringing her out, which was accordingly performed with much gallantry by Captain <hi>Southwood,</hi> and Captain <hi>Falconer</hi> in deſpight of 500. ſmall ſhot that lined the banks, and endeavoured (but in vain) to Impede them.</p>
            <p>With this prize (being the firſt taken upon that Coaſt) he ſteered to <hi>Kinſale;</hi> where arriving, the Lord <hi>Broghill,</hi> then Commander in chiefe of the Parliament Forces in <hi>Munſter,</hi> being in great neceſſity, uſed ſome arguments to induce him to ſell part of the prize there for ready money, and to ſupply him therewith, by which the Soldiers would be releeved, and he being thereby enabled to take the field, the intereſt of Parl. would be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advanced, (with which he complyed) as not holding his own intereſt any way compatible, when the publick was in ballance, as an evidence whereof he ſold all or the greateſt part of the beſt goods for ready money, ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him therewith, and received Bills charged upon the Parliament, upon which accompt there remaines to this day unſatisfied 3331.</p>
            <p>The forementioned ſervices and evidences of his Faith and affection ſo much to the knowledge of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by repreſentations from ſeverall places, ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, that a Commiſſion was ſent him from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Admiralty, to be Commander in chief of the aforeſaid Squadron, and all ſuch other Ships as he could ſet out, or procure to joyne with him, which Ships were to follow his directions; whereupon hearing that the enemy was fortifying in the Iſle of <hi>Cape Cleere,</hi> which being known to the Lord <hi>Inchequeen</hi> alſo (who was newly arrived there) and perceiving the evill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137214:6"/>thereof, ſent Cap: <hi>Williams</hi> a Commiſſion to land thereon, with deſire if poſſible to force the enemy out, and to ſecure the ſame for the ſervice of the Parl. which he accordingly effected without the loſſe of one man; the enemy being forc'd to ſurrender upon quarter and promiſe of Tranſport to the maine Land, leaving all their Armes, Ammunition and Spoile behind them, which booty being moſt in Cattle and valued at 250. l. was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually divided amongſt the Marriners, Captain <hi>Williams</hi> disburſing the money, and retaining the Cattle there for the better ſupport of the place.</p>
            <p>Having reduc'd the ſaid Iſland as aforeſaid, and took an exact view thereof, and finding the ſame (although of a ſmall value) in reſpect of it ſelf, yet very conſiderable to the State, as lying convenient to ſecure or prejudice the Southern and Weſterne trade, he firſt put in 35. able Seamen to ſecure the Caſtle, who remained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in untill he had procured it to be engarriſoned with a Lieutenant and 46. Soldiers of the Lord <hi>Inchequeens</hi> Army, which were maintained at his own charge; ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he repayred the Caſtle, and furniſhed it with ſuitable proviſions of all ſorts, to his great expence, not doubting but when upon examination it ſhould appear what preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the Parliament would have ſuſtained, had the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my poſſeſſed the ſame, he ſhould have received an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvverable ſatisfaction for his ſaid ſervices and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>The Iſland being ſetled, he againe put to Sea, and took the Ship Cat of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> laden with Salt and Tobacco, of which he made a man of Warre, and added her to his Squadron, but ranging to and fro upon the Iriſh coaſt for ſecurity of that Channell, all the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Ships being called off, the winter growing on,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137214:6"/>and having by ſtreſſe of weather loſt the <hi>Charls</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Frigots, he with the Mermaid and Warſpite returned for <hi>England,</hi> leaving the Cat on that Coaſt, who ſoone after took in the River of <hi>Limbrick</hi> a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable prize, but he himſelfe in <hi>England,</hi> they carryed her into <hi>Kinſale,</hi> and imbezel'd moſt of the goods, ſo that little advantage accrewed thereby; In which ſervices ſucceſſively, there is due to him for victualling, 620l. from the State, as may appeare by Bills ſigned by the Commiſſioners of the Navy.</p>
            <p>But the beſt ſervices many times receive the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence or reſpect, as may appeare by the ſubſequent part of this Narrative: for Capt: <hi>Williams</hi> his neceſſitated reſidence in <hi>England</hi> to procure from the Parl. the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their engagements to him, their non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the 333. l. due upon the Lo: <hi>Broghills</hi> Bills, nor the 620. l. due for victualling, as aforeſaid, the charge of his Garriſon in Cape Cleere, his family and friends in <hi>England</hi> ruin'd by the Enemie, together with the viſible neceſſity lay upon him to ſupply the ſaid Garriſon with men, in lieu of thoſe of the Lord <hi>Inchequeens,</hi> which were to march to their Regiment at <hi>Cork,</hi> reduced him to ſo great a neceſsity (againſt which he could ſee no viſible poſsibility of obtaining reliefe from the Parl. or Com. of Safety in one caſe or other) that he which but few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths before was able and reſolved to ſet forth to Sea, in the publique ſervice with four men of Warre, a Gally, and two Brigandines, was hereby ſo diſenabled, that he was forced to ſell a Conſiderable part thereof, only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to himſelfe the Mermaid and the two Brigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines entire; which having effected, and knowing the time nigh expiring, wherein the Lord <hi>Inchequeens</hi> men were to returne to their Regiment, and ſeeing little like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137214:7"/>of gaining any thing from the Parliament or Com, of ſafety, that might conduce to the ſeaſonable and effectuall ſettlement of the ſaid Garriſon and Iſle, by reaſon of the daily encreaſe of new troubles; he was forced at his owne charge to ſend his Brother, Captain <hi>John Williams</hi> into <hi>Wales</hi> to raiſe and tranſport 30. men to engarriſon the ſaid Iſland, and to furniſh them with all neceſſary ſupplyes that might enable them to ſecure the ſame, which work he ſodainly effected, and arrived there in due time; the Lord <hi>Inchequeens</hi> men being called off, and the charge thereof committed to him, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly whereupon the Lord <hi>Inchequeen</hi> Revolted from his obedience to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>By which meanes, to the forementioned troubles a new one was added, and that of a much greater concernment; for by this revolt of the Lord <hi>Inchequeen</hi>'s the ſaid Iſland of <hi>Cape Cleere,</hi> was in danger to be loſt, as to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Whereupon waving all other concernments, hee addreſſed himſelfe to the then Committee of Safety, and laid before them the conſideration of the place, with all the advantages, that by the ſecurity thereof would accrew to the publique, but could obtaine nothing but a ſingle Order to enable him to take care thereof, and a promiſe of neceſſary ſupply, although to this day he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any.</p>
            <p>But being engaged to improve his utmoſt abilities, to preſerve the ſaid Iſland, and finding no poſſibility of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining any recruit either of Men, Proviſions, Armes, Ammunition or Cloaths; his own eſtate being nigh ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined, and the Iſland no way able to reſiſt the power of the Enemy; he immediatly diſpatched complementall letters to the Lord <hi>Inchequeen</hi> to amuſe and divert him from deſigning or attempting any thing againſt the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:137214:7"/>
            <p>Immediatly whereupon, (having firſt obtained a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Committee of the Admiralty, to Captain <hi>Crowder</hi> Admirall of the Iriſh Seas, that he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute his utmoſt aſſiſtance in ſecuring the ſaid Iſland) and having alſo with ſome difficulty obtained an Order from the Committee of the Navy for the payment of 400l. in courſe from Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> then Treaſurer, as ſatisfaction for the victualling of his two Ships, the Helena and Mermaid; but no ready money being to be had thereon he was neceſſitated to take up 200l. upon Bottomry, for which he paid 350l. as principall, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture for 8. months 100l. upon ſpecialty in <hi>London,</hi> and 150l. in <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> ſo great was his charge in victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and procuring 60. Seamen beſides Soldiers, by him taken up to be employed in the ſaid ſervice.</p>
            <p>Being by the extraordinary appearance of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to paſſe through all theſe difficulties, and out at Sea in the Mermayd, a dangerous combination was ſet on foot by ſome ill-affected perſons, officers in the ſaid Ships, who deſigned to cary the Ships to <hi>Illford</hi> Sluce, where the revolted Ships then lay; but the ſame was through mercy diſcovered and prevented, and the offenders ſeized and ſecured in the Parliament Garriſon at <hi>Tenby</hi> in <hi>Wales.</hi> From whence, as ſoon as a ſupply could be got, to anſwer the number of the forementioned Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, he ſet ſayle for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in few dayes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived before the harbor of <hi>Kinſale,</hi> where coming to an Anchor without command, he writ another letter to the Lord <hi>Inchequeen,</hi> therein intimating, that according to his former letters he was come upon the coaſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with only one Ship; with which he was Commiſſioned to take upon the Iriſh by the Parliament, which ſervice he was neceſſitated for 6. months to undertake as well to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137214:8"/>repayre his fortunes ruined by the Iriſh, as to recover a coſiderable ſumme of money due to him for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſervice; and therefore deſired his Lordſhip to take no notice of him for that time, but command the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a Brigantine by him built and remaining in harbour, and that he might have proviſion for his money, for which favour he ſhould remaine (ſetting aſide the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid neceſsity) his Lordſhips moſt faithfull and obedient ſervant, &amp;c. With which Letter the Lord <hi>Inchequeen</hi> was ſo fully ſatisfied, that he not onely ordered the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Kinſalle,</hi> but all the other Engliſh Garriſons, to let Capt: <hi>Williams</hi> have what he deſired for his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and his Brigantine was ſent out accordingly, with which he immediately ſet ſayle to <hi>Cape Cleere,</hi> where ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving, his Brother and Officers came aboard him, to whom he gave ſuitable inſtructions how to manage their buſineſſe, competent ſupplyes to enable them thereto, and exchange of Soldiers for feare of deficiencie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, together with an aſſurance of not onely frequent Viſits, but Supplyes, as neceſſity ſhould require.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſecured the Iſland, he ſayled toward the River of <hi>Limbrick,</hi> where hee took a ſmall Prize, which in his returning to <hi>Cape Cleere</hi> was loſt by foule weather. Soone after he met with a Dutch ſhip laden with Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants goods, and bound for <hi>Limbrick,</hi> which he reſolved to ſecure in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> but Providence ordered it otherwiſe, as by the ſequel may appeare; and that diſpen fation which he thought to be of a deſtructive tendencie, proved the onely meanes of the preſervation of the ſaid Iſland. For,</p>
            <p>Sailing along the Coaſt, the wind being at N. N. Weſt, betwixt <hi>Kinſale</hi> and the River of <hi>Corke,</hi> in the faire way, the Tide being very low, and his Prize ahead ſome few Ships length, ſhe ſtruck her Rudder againſt a Rock, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137214:8"/>went over without any conſiderable detriment: but Cap: <hi>Williams</hi> ſayling ſpeedily after, before ever they could by weaſle, Gunne, or other ſignall give notice, his Ship draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more water, ſtruck ſo violently, that 7. foot of one ſide of her Keele was broke off; and had ſhe not been a very ſtrong Ship, ſhe had ſunk down right, but with much labour the Pump kept her ſwimming: however he was forced to ſtand for <hi>Kinſale,</hi> where comming to an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor as formerly, without Command, and not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any boat to come aboard him, for feare of diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his neceſſity; he writ againe to my Lord <hi>Inchequeen,</hi> and in four dayes obtained an Order to come into <hi>Port,</hi> to enjoy ſecurity there, with liberty to put his prize to ſale, and aſſurance that he ſhould be free to diſpoſe of himſelfe and affaires at his owne diſcretion, &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he went into <hi>Port,</hi> haled his Ship aſhore to be mended and expos'd to ſale, the ſaid prize.</p>
            <p>While this was on foot, Captain <hi>Pen</hi> came with the Nonſuch Frigot into <hi>Kingſale</hi> with the Lord <hi>Inchequeens</hi> eldeſt Sonne, to whom he went privatly and acquainted him how affaires ſtood with him, together with the reaſon of his being there, and by him to enform the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of his deſigne, with the knowledge whereof he could not truſt any of his owne party.</p>
            <p>But Capt: <hi>Williams</hi> his condition, not being publickly known, ſome Gentlemen carried from <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> reported at <hi>Tinby</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> that he was revolted with the Lord <hi>Inchequeen,</hi> whereupon a ketch by him taken formerly from a <hi>Wexford</hi> man, was ſeized on for the uſe of the State, but his Brother together with Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Horton</hi> and Col: <hi>Jones,</hi> making an addreſſe unto the Admirall, who knew Capt <hi>Williams</hi> integrity, cauſed her to be returned; in whoſe cuſtody ſhe remained ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137214:9"/>months, till afterward upon a ſcandalous Petition fraught with ſundry falſe ſuggeſtions preſented to the Generalls, ſhe was ordered and delivered to a <hi>Dover</hi> man, that owned her ſome yeers before; whereby he was damnified nigh 300l.</p>
            <p>But though it was his unhappineſſe to ſuffer cauſeleſly, his enſuing actions manifeſted that his affection was not reſident with his body in <hi>Kinſale,</hi> for he had no ſooner repayred his Ship, but he prepared to put to Sea, in which juncture of time, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted Fleet came thither; who by an Order in favour of the <hi>Limbrick</hi> Merchants, notwithſtanding <hi>Inchequeens</hi> engagement to the contrary) cauſed his Goods to be ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; but afterwards by the procurement of the Lo: <hi>Inche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queen,</hi> they vvere againe freed; but with ſo much regret on the part of the Princes Adherents, that he went not onely in great danger of his life, but was left without all viſible poſſibility (without an extraordinary providence) either to get his Ship to <hi>England,</hi> or ſecure the Iſland of <hi>Cape Cleere.</hi> Whereupon to eſcape their malice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance to get his Ship into their Fleet, he deſigned her for a Voyage to the Weſt Indies with Paſſengers, which with much difficulty was effected, a Kinſman of his being truſted therewith; who at his returne was by him orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to touch at <hi>Cape Cleere.</hi> That deſigne being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, he then caſt about how to ſecure the ſaid Iſland untill the arrivall of the Engliſh Army, which he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Spring, and the return of the ſaid Ship. In order to which end, (after he had ſold the remains of his goods, and performed ſuch formalities to the Prince and Lo: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequeen</hi> as his condition enforced) he betook himſelf to the Iſland, where he remained, untill he received intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the loſſe of his Ship and goods, to the value of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137214:9"/>3000.l. and the arrivall of the ſo long hoped and expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Army from <hi>England,</hi> under the command of the now Lo: Generall <hi>Comwell;</hi> to whom as ſoone as convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was afforded him, he made a tender of his ſervice, (ſome moneths before manifeſted by Letter to the Lord <hi>Broghill</hi>) which was received vvith evident teſtimonies of good will, and his ſervices and affection acknowledged, with promiſe of future favours; but the Generall being by publique affaires withdrawn from that ſervice, ſome perſons to whom the management of affaires were (as to the ſecuring of <hi>Cape Cleere</hi>) committed, who (as belce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) were parties to the former falſe repreſentation of his revolt; although they were now convinced of their error, yet apprehending they had juſtly prejudiced him againſt them, inſtead of ſalving the breach, withheld the reliefe intended for the Iſland, ſo that he was not onely a third time ruined in his Eſtate, but alſo the ſaid Iſland and Garriſon endangered to be loſt to the Enemy, who took encouragement by his neceſſitated abſence to attempt the beſieging thereof, as by the following particulars will be undenyably evident.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by ſome under-hand ſuggeſtions they endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to diſpoſſeſſe him of the Command of the ſaid Iſland, which being by the confident aſſertions of Sir <hi>Hardres Waller,</hi> and a perfect narrative of his ſervices &amp; ſuffering, tendred to, and conſidered by the Lord Generall, cleared and removed, he had his Commiſſion ſigned and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Order that direction ſhould be given to Col: <hi>Fayer</hi> Governour of <hi>Corke,</hi> to ſettle an eſtabliſhment for the ſaid Caſtle and Iſland, but notwithſtanding all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, that was for night three weeks obſtructed, in which time Providence diſperſed the enemy by meanes of a diſcontent that aroſe among themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:137214:10"/>
            <p>At length with much importunity, he obtained two files of Muskettiers, and an Officer, as a Recruit on the States pay, which were continued only one month in the Garriſon, and then ſent for away, unleſſe Capt: <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> would maintaine them at his owne charge; neither were they content with this, but by ſome underhand working with the Commiſſioners for the Revenue, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the Iſland to be offered at a Rent to who would give moſt: to colour which proceedings, a letter they ſhewed C: <hi>Williams,</hi> as pretended to be ſent from the Lord Deputy <hi>Ireton,</hi> although it be evident by the purport thereof, if any ſuch letter were ſent by the Lo: Deputy; it was occaſioned by ſome letter firſt writ to him, deſiring his direction therein, otherwiſe he would never have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in anſwer; amongſt ſeverall other things, that unleſſe they could prove Capt: <hi>Williams</hi> a Delinquent, it was but reaſon he ſhould keep the Iſland, paying a Rent, &amp;c. whereupon he ſeeing the deſigne of his enemies was to take all poſſible occaſions to eject him, he ſaw rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and neceſſity to countermine them, to which end he ſubmitted to a Rent, without Capitulation, whereupon 30l. <hi>per an.</hi> was impoſed, and he enjoyned at his charge, to keepe Guard in the Caſtle, which contract being ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, he returned to the Iſland.</p>
            <p>But the enemy perceiving how he was ſlighted, and that he was no way likely to receive any aſſiſtance or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe from the adjacent Garriſons, of which it is ſuppoſed they had intimation before hand, (as by the ſequell if compared will appear probable) immediatly united as one man, contributing out of every family, upon an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition for re-taking the ſaid Iſland, as a place moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for their refuge under the conduct of <hi>Cornelius O Driſcoll,</hi> who was a perſon in quarter, but was made
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137214:10"/>Colonell for that defigne, who with the aſſiſtance of <hi>Oſolivan Beare,</hi> who furniſhed Armes, Boats, Ordnance, and the like, and fifty of the moſt bloody Rogues in that part of the Countrey, having levyed their forces, they ſetled at <hi>Crooke</hi> Haven, ſome four Leagues from <hi>Cape Cleere,</hi> there expecting an opportunity of tranſport and landing: for prevention whereof, Captain <hi>Williams</hi> deſigned his brother Captain <hi>John,</hi> to goe to Sea with a Boat man'd with ten Muskettiers, to ſee if he could fall into their quarters, and ſeize, burne or ſinke their Boats, provided for their Tranſport, which failing, upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne he was purſued with three of the enemies Boats, with whom he was forced to engage, and with whom he continued a deſperate fight, many of the enemies being ſlaine, and their Boats forced to retire; after which, Captaine <hi>John Williams</hi> being by Gods providence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, with all his men, who received ſeverall wounds, but none mortall, returned ſafe to the Iſland.</p>
            <p>Soon after he received information that the enemy had appointed a Rendevouze at a place on the maine, two Leagues from the Iſland, whereupon he a ſecond time ſent out his Brother Captaine <hi>John Williams,</hi> with a ſmall Skiffe manned, to the end he might fall in among them, to ſpoile their Boats, but the weather proving tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, he took onely three, which by reaſon of the foulneſſe of the weather, being diſenabled to bring them to <hi>Cape Gleere,</hi> he carryed and ſecured at the next Engliſh Garriſon; from whence he had foure Leagues to Row to <hi>Cape Cleere</hi> in foule weather, againſt the wind in a darke foggy night; but neceſſities overcoming all difficulties, to Sea he put, and being with much hazard got almoſt home, he fell among the enemies Boats, who were viewing a place where they intended to attempt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137214:11"/>Landing, but being diſcovered by the enemy, a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie aroſe between them whether it was an Engliſh Boat, or one of their owne Company; during which diſpute he made a ſhift to get a ſmall Rock betweene him and them, by which meanes he eſcaped, and got himſelf and moſt of his men ſafe on ſhore, and to the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>But having no conſiderable ſtrength, could no way fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impede their deſigne, or prevent their landing, but was conſtrained to endure a ſiege by 600. men, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly made their approaches within Piſtoll ſhot of the Caſtle, where they raiſed a Battery, planted their Ordnance, and ſent a ſummons to ſurrender the Caſtle upon good termes, but he denying to treat or ſurrender, they fell to battering the Caſtle, and ſpending ſmall ſhot upon all places where they thought to annoy him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to ſmall purpoſe, whereupon in a dark night they attempted a ſtorme, but were repulſed, with the loſſe of 19. of their ſtouteſt men, which were left dead under the walls, without any loſſe received by him in the ſaid Caſtle.</p>
            <p>The enemy ſeeing no probability of obtaining the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, onely continued their ſiege five or ſix dayes, till they had carryed away all his cattle, and ſtock in the Iſland, to the value of 800. l. as it was by Oath proved by order of the Commiſſioners of the Revenue. After which they marched away, and returned to their ſeverall homes, and were received into quarter upon promiſe to pay contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; his loſſes and ſufferings being not deemed conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be put in the ballance, that he ſhould merit repaire from that enemy.</p>
            <p>For returne of which favour, within a ſhort time after that very enemy fell into Rebellion againe, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many outrages. Whereupon the Lo: <hi>Broghill</hi> fell into their quarters, to whom the Commiſſioners of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137214:11"/>writ a Letter, deſiring him out of what prey he might or ſhould take, to repaire Capt: <hi>Williams;</hi> but although he took all their Cattle, Capt: <hi>Williams</hi> could reap no bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereby, in reſpect a precedent Order was pretended to be made by the Commiſſioners; whereby it was directed that all prey ſhould be ſold, and two thirds of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue paid into the Treaſury, and the other to the party engaged in the action. In this manner, contrary to all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer preſidents, (it being uſuall to repaire the Engliſh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Baronies that prejudiced them) he was left without poſſibility of reliefe for his dammage ſuſtained by that Enemy.</p>
            <p>And therefore the premiſſes being duly weighed, and a ſerious conſideration had both of his ſervices and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, it is very much hoped, That both your Excellency, and all perſons of worth and authority, will be pleaſed to caſt a favourable eye and reſpect towards him, and ſpeedily and effectually provide for his full reparation, and juſt ſatisfaction of whatſoever ſhall be made appeare to have been disburſed by him, or wherein ſoever he hath been damnified in ſervice of the publick. To give light wherein, be pleaſed to examine the following account.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>By his being imployed in the taking, fortifying, and ſecuring the ſame, he hath loſt his Sea-imployment; in which if he had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, would have yeelded him a conſiderable Revenue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The loſſe of his owne Ship, worth</hi> — 3000. l. — 0 — 0</item>
               <item>3. <hi>The loſſe of the</hi> Increaſe <hi>and</hi> Charges <hi>Frigots, with a Brigandine employed in defence of the ſaid Iſland, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Ketch del. by order of the Gen. to the value of</hi> 500. l.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>For Victualling due to him</hi> — 1033. l.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>There is expended by him in taking, fortifying, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and defending the ſaid Caſtle and Iſland, as by an exact account will appeare,</hi> — 3000. l.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>For damage ſuſtained by the Siege, &amp; loſſe of his cattle</hi> — 800. l.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:137214:12"/>
            <p>By all which it may appeare, if duly examined, that by the preſervation of that Iſle and Garriſon, he is damnified above 8000. l.</p>
            <p>Beſides the loſs of his employment at Sea, which if improved, might have rendered him capable of a more then ordinary relation; over and above the probable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate that he might juſtly have accumulated to himſelfe in his ordinary command as Captain.</p>
            <p>But the forementioned loſſes and accidents ariſing thereupon, did reduce him to great neceſſity, his charge being certain and great, his debts contracted upon him for ſupport of the Garriſon, and other his relations nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and no viſible poſſibility left him of repaying the one, or ſupplying the other.</p>
            <p>Whereupon ſeeing his endevours at Land, ſuted not to his deſires, he reſolved as his laſt refuge to try his own proper element, the Sea; to which purpoſe he built him a ſmall Frigot, which being man'd and fitted, he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſet Sayle, and had ſuddainly an opportunity of relieving two New-found Land ſhips, the one of <hi>Poole</hi> the other of <hi>Weymouth,</hi> the ſame being taken by the <hi>French,</hi> both which were reſtored to their proper owners. To conclude, after ſeverall skirmiſhes, loſſes, hardſhips and hazards, God was pleaſed as a returne of his prayers, and reward of his induſtry and patience, to give him an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to take upon the <hi>French,</hi> whereby he hath been enabled to pay a conſiderable part of his debts, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his relations during the time of his Petitioning the Parliament to take his Caſe, Sufferings, Expences and Services into conſideration; to the end the ſaid Iſland of <hi>Cape Cleere,</hi> never worth in times of peace above 100. l. <hi>per an.</hi> having been by him reduc'd ſo many yeers ſince, and maintained at his charge, might in conſideration of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137214:12"/>his ſaid Services and Arreares be ſetled upon him and his Heires, he engaging to plant it with Engliſh, who ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame without any charge to the State, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive debentures for his disburſements. In returne of which favour, if he had or could obtaine, (although his Arreares due for the keeping thereof, would according to the uſuall valuation have purchaſed a much better e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) it would create an exceeding obligation in point of gratitude upon him, and futurely devote him, his abilities, life and eſtate, faithfully to be imployed and improved for advancement of the publick intereſt.</p>
            <p>But God which is the wiſe diſpoſer of all things, hath ſo ordered affaires, that his endeavours have been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fruitleſſe; only he is kept up by a principle of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, nay confidence, that though one Generation be paſſed away, that might have beene inſtrumentall in repayring not onely his breach, but the breaches of the Nation, yet that the time is at hand, wherein every man that hath with Faith, Affection and Fervour laid out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and eſtate, for defence of the publique, ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably repayred, according to their ſervices and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; In aſſurance whereof, he hath (principles of reaſon and neceſſity inducing) taken the boldneſſe to draw up and preſent unto ſerious conſideration this Narrative; In hope that when an opportunity ſhall be offered, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many others may be remembred and repaired by the payment of his disburſements and arrears, or ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid Iſland of <hi>Cape Cleere</hi> upon him and his heires, as deſired for ſatisfaction thereof.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis Narrative of my little peregrinations and ſervices for this Nation, (yet not without many dangers and croſſes to my ſelf) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137214:13"/>with the hard meaſure I have hither to found where I had hopes of better, being prepared for the true information of all ſuch as either ingeniouſly deſire the ſame, or whoſe worth and authority may juſtly expect to be ſatisfied therein. I have preſumed (yet in all humility) to addreſſe, more especially to your Excellency, in regard I found both in your ſelfe and your honoured ſon the Lord Deputy</hi> Ireton, <hi>ſo cleere a judgement of my actions in</hi> Ireland, <hi>ſo free from diſtorting things to the worſt; ſo ſenſible of what a Soldier (without ſuspicion to his faith) might doe when ſurrounded with difficulties, as was ſometimes my caſe with the Lo:</hi> Inchequeen. <hi>Thus as I muſt ever honor the memory of ſo large a worth and ſo cleer a goodneſſe, ſo when occaſion ſhall make me happy, I ſhall thankefully teſtifie to the uttermoſt of my abilities; And as I was bleſt</hi> there, <hi>with this favour from you, which (had not others envied) had eas'd me of this publication, and unwelcome ſpeaking of my ſelfe; ſo muſt I with all thankfulneſſe acknowledge, that in all my late long attendance upon the Parl, to have my ſervices and ſufferings taken into conſideration, I have found none more ready and forward then your Excellencie. And now my Lord, my hopes upon the late Parliament ending with its diſſolution, there is not any in this world ſo capable of miniſtring reliefe to my languiſhing condition; nor (as I have good cauſe to believe) ſo inclinable to do me right as your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and therefore if where I have found the greateſt vertue and readineſſe to help, I preſſe with more importunity then well becomes me: Let my neceſſity ſomewhat excuſe; and beare it I beſeech you, as the greateſt goodneſſe hath ever beene accustomed; and be pleaſed to favour me yet ſo far forth as to put my humble deſires herein expreſſed into ſome ſpeedy way of tryall, as to the justneſſe of them, and when they ſhall ſo appeare, into as speedy a courſe for their attainment. To which end, a Petition to the Councell of State is in readines, that by your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies favourable protection, both my ſelfe and Family may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and encouraged; and be preſerved from that calamity, miſery, and reproach, which malicious and ill affected perſons wiſh unto us for our conſtant affection to this Common-wealth, and faithfull adherence to your Excellencie, for whoſe fruition of all temporall and eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe ſhall ever pray,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble Servant, <hi>REEVE WILLIAMS.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
